<!DOCTYPE module SYSTEM "module.dtd">

<module name="sonar_i2c" dir="sonar">
  <doc>
    <description>
    A Sonar with I2C connection can be used as unidirectional rangefinder. Examples of devices are e.g. Maxbotix MB1240 or a GY-US42V2.
    The sensor can be used as a distance-measuring tool to detect the range (distance) to a surfaces. Usecase for example: AGL hold,terrain following or landing assist.

    To be able to use the I2C version of a Sonar, add this module to your airframe and set needed parameters.

    Notes:
    + The maximum useful detection distance is 4m for common sonar based small sized sensors, even if datasheet e.g. states 7m.
    For most I2C sonar range devices, a sampling rate of at least 15Hz is supported. However, if measurements are taken at longer distances, 
    the time required for the ultrasonic pulse to return increases, which may limit the maximum achievable sampling rate. 
    It is recommended to adjust the SONAR_I2C_PERIODIC_FREQUENCY parameter according to the sensor's capabilities and the expected measurement range to ensure reliable readings.

    + If the distance is read but the scale is incorrect, adjust the SONAR_I2C_SCALE parameter to match the sensor's specifications.
    The scale factor can also be determined experimentally by measuring a known distance and adjusting the scale until the output matches the expected value.

    + If the sensor is used in an airframe with landing gear, it is recommended to set the SONAR_I2C_OFFSET to the height of the landing gear, so that the AGL value is correct. 
    Keep in mind that most sonar sensors have a deadzone of 0.15m to 0.25m, so the AGL cannot be measured if landinggear shorter than the deadzone range.

    + There is an option to compensate the AGL value for body rotation, which is useful if e.g. a roll maneuver, the sensor is not pointing straight down it compensates the AGL value for the body rotation.
    
    + Also an option to filter the sensor output is available, which is useful if the sensor is noisy or has a lot of outliers, in cas of a sonar, almost always the case.
    
    + An option to set a different I2C address is available in some hardware but not implemented to set dynamically in this driver. 
    Use external tools to change the I2C address if needed and set the SONAR_I2C_ADDR parameter accordingly.

    + Distance compensation for pressure and temperature are not implemented, keep in mind that sonar sensors are susceptible to temperature and pressure changes. 

    + To set the minimum and maximum range the sensor can reliably measure, use the SONAR_I2C_MIN_RANGE and SONAR_I2C_MAX_RANGE parameters.
      Note that if rotation compensation is enabled, the effective maximum range will be reduced when the vehicle rolls or pitches.
      If it is impossible to measure the distance reliable, the distance value will be set to NAN (not a number).

    + To restrict the AGL range define it in your airframefile with AGL_DIST_SONAR_MAX and AGL_DIST_SONAR_MIN

    </description>   
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_DEV" value="i2cX" description="I2C device port on flightcontroller to use for this device, e.g i2c2"/>
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_ADDR" value="0xE0" description="The I2C Slave address in 8bit of this device"/>
    <configure name="USE_SONAR_I2C_AGL" value="TRUE|FALSE" description="Updates the AGL value in state,if not defined, defaults to FALSE"/>
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_COMPENSATE_ROTATION" value="TRUE|FALSE" description="Compensate AGL measurements for body rotation. Disabled by default"/>
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_PERIODIC_FREQUENCY" value="30" description="Sensor readings in HZ"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_USE_FILTER" value="TRUE|FALSE" description="If this is enabled, a median filter on the distance output, defaults to TRUE"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_MEDIAN_SIZE" value="11" description="If median filter is enabled then set this option to filter the output more(or less), default is 7"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_SCALE" value="0.00006" description="Sensor scale for raw sensor output to a meter unit conversion, "/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_OFFSET" value="0.56"  description="Sensor offset in meters, as in where one wants zero to be, default is 0.0"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_MIN_RANGE" value="0.33" unit="m" description="If defined, set limit to minimum value the sensor can reliably measure, default 0.25m"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_MAX_RANGE" value="6.0" unit="m" description="If defined, set limit to maximum value the sensor can reliably measure, default 4.0m"/>
    <define name="MODULE_SONAR_I2C_SYNC_SEND" value="TRUE|FALSE" description="Send RAW and scaled message with each new measurement,useful for debugging sensor issues (default: FALSE)"/>
  </doc>

  <settings>
    <dl_settings NAME="Rangefinder">
      <dl_settings NAME="Sonar I2C">
        <dl_setting MAX="1" MIN="0" STEP="1" VAR="sonar_i2c.update_agl" shortname="Update AGL"/>
      </dl_settings>
    </dl_settings>
  </settings>
  <dep>
    <depends>i2c</depends>
    <provides>sonar</provides>
  </dep>

  <header>
    <file name="sonar_i2c.h"/>
  </header>
  <init fun="sonar_i2c_init()"/>
  <periodic fun="sonar_i2c_periodic()" freq="SONAR_I2C_PERIODIC_FREQUENCY"/>
  <periodic fun="sonar_i2c_report()" freq="10" autorun="FALSE"/>
  <event fun="sonar_i2c_event()"/>
  <makefile>
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_DEV" default="i2c1" case="lower|upper"/>
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_ADDR" default="0xE0"/>
    <configure name="USE_SONAR_I2C_AGL" default="0"/>
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_COMPENSATE_ROTATION" default="0"/>
    <configure name="SONAR_I2C_PERIODIC_FREQUENCY" default="30"/>
    <define name="USE_$(SONAR_I2C_DEV_UPPER)"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_DEV" value="$(SONAR_I2C_DEV_LOWER)"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_ADDR" value="$(SONAR_I2C_ADDR)"/>
    <define name="USE_SONAR_I2C_AGL" value="$(USE_SONAR_I2C_AGL)"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_COMPENSATE_ROTATION" value="$(SONAR_I2C_COMPENSATE_ROTATION)"/>
    <define name="SONAR_I2C_PERIODIC_FREQUENCY" value="$(SONAR_I2C_PERIODIC_FREQUENCY)"/>
    <file name="sonar_i2c.c"/>
  </makefile>
  <makefile target="nps">
    <define name="USE_SONAR" value="TRUE"/><!-- in NPS use a virtual sonar to simulate rangeing measurements -->
  </makefile>
</module>
